我们现在要描述一些略微数学概念，但它们非常有用，
We’re now going to describe some slightly mathematical concepts but they’re very useful,
所以忍受我。
so bear with me.
到目前为止，当我们谈论机器人时，我们一直在谈论关节
So far, when we’ve been talking about robots, we’ve been talking a lot about the joint
角。
angles.
我们现在要做的是概括这个概念，我们将参考
What we’re going to do now is to generalize that concept and we’re going to refer to
概括联合坐标。
generalize joint coordinates.
现在，对于关节旋转的大多数机器人来说，就是它们的旋转时间关节，
Now, for most robots where the joints are revolute, that is their rotating time joints,
那么它们的广义联合坐标就是联合角度。
then their generalize joint coordinate is simply the joint angle.
但是，对于那些有滑动关节的少数机器人也被称为棱柱形
But, for those small number of robots that have got a sliding joint also known as a prismatic
关节，则广义关节坐标则为长度，即长度
joint, then the generalize joint coordinate then would be a length, the length of that
滑动关节。
sliding joint.
因此，概括联合坐标只是我们可以处理机器人关节的一种方式
So, generalize joint coordinate is simply a way that we can deal with robot joints that
旋转或滑动。
either rotate or slide.
因此，机器人的所有关节坐标的集合我们称为关节配置。
So, the set of all joint coordinates for the robot we referred to as the joint configuration.
它是一个向量，通常用符号Q表示。并且，向量的长度是
It’s a vector and typically denoted by the symbol Q. And, the length of the vector is
N和N是关节的数量。
N and N is the number of joints.
因此，关节配置Q是长度为N的向量，并且该向量的元素也是
So, joint configuration Q is a vector of length N and the elements of that vector are either
角度或长度。
an angle or a length.
关节角度向量属于空间，空间C。
The joint angle vector belongs to a space, the space C.
我们将此称为配置空间。
We refer to this as the configuration space.
关节配置属于集合C，C是所有可能的关节配置的集合。
The joint configurations belong to the set C and C is the set of all possible joint configurations.
现在，C是N维实数空间的子集。
Now, C is a subset of the N dimensional real number space.
当我们谈论机器人时，另一个非常重要的空间就是空间
The other space that’s really important when we’re talking about robots is the space
所有可能的末端效应器姿势，我们用符号T来指代。我们这样说
of all possible end effector poses and we refer to this by the symbol T. We say that
末端效应器姿势ksiE属于集合T，即所有可能的末端效应器的集合
the end effector pose ksi E belongs to the set T, the set of all possible end effector
构成。
poses.
在二维中，T是所有可能的平移和旋转的子集。
In two dimensions, T is a subset of all possible translations and rotations.
而且，它是一个子集的原因是机器人只有有限的范围。
And, the reason that it’s a subset is that the robot has only got finite reach.
它无法触及地平线。
It can’t reach out to the horizon.
例如，因此T是二维中所有可能位置和方向的子集。
For example, so T is a subset of all possible positions and orientations in two dimensions.
例如，我们已经看过简单描述末端执行器姿势的机器人
For example, we’ve looked at robots where the end effector pose is simply described
通过坐标X和Y.
by the coordinates X and Y.
我们还看了一些机器人，其中末端效应器的姿势由位置描述
We’ve also looked at some robots where the end effector pose is described by the position
X和Y以及方向Theta。
X and Y and by the orientation Theta.
在三个维度中，我们会说T是SE3的子集，即所有可能位置的集合
In three dimensions, we would say that T is a subset of SE3, the set of all possible positions
和三维空间中的方向。
and orientations in three dimensional space.
并且，我们再次查看描述末端效应器姿势的一些具体示例
And, we’ve, again, look at some specific examples where the end effector pose is described
就其位置X，Y和Z而言，一些机器人是末端执行器所构成的
just in terms of its position, X, Y and Z, some robots where the end effector pose is
由位置X，Y和Z以及单个俯仰角描述。
described by position X, Y and Z and a single pitch angle.
我们还研究了一些机器人，它们的末端执行器可以用来描述
We’ve also looked at some robots whose end effector can be described in terms of the
例如，位置X，Y和Z以及定向滚动，俯仰和偏转角度。
position X, Y and Z and orientation roll, pitch and yaw angles for example.
这些都是SE3的子集。
These are all subsets of SE3.
接下来重要的考虑因素是这些不同空间的尺寸
The next important consideration then is the dimensions of these different spaces, the
任务空间，我们描述末端执行器姿势的空间，以及配置
task space, the space in which we describe the pose of the end effector, and the configuration
我们描述机器人关节坐标的空间。
space in which we describe the joint coordinates of the robot.
我们说机器人有很多自由度，而且数量相等
We say that a robot has got so many degrees of freedom and that’s equal to the number
机器人具有的关节，这是其配置空间的尺寸。
of joints the robot has and that’s the dimension of its configuration space.
所以，如果一个机器人有三个关节，那么我们就说它的配置空间已经到了
So, if a robot has got three joints, then we say that its configuration space has got
三个维度。
three dimensions.
同样，我们可以谈论任务空间中的自由度
Similarly, we could talk about the degrees of freedom in the task space and that’s
等于任务空间T的尺寸。考虑一个简单的平面机器人的姿势。
equal to the dimension of the task space T. Consider the pose of a simple planar robot.
它的末端执行器姿势简单地由两个坐标X和Y描述。
Its end effector pose is described simply by the two coordinates X and Y.
在这种情况下，任务空间的维度为2。
In this case, the dimension of a task space is 2.
如果它是具有三个关节的平面机器人，则可以描述末端执行器姿势
If it’s a planar robot with three joints, then the end effector pose can be described
通过X和Y位置以及方向Theta。
by the X and Y position and the orientation Theta.
在这种情况下，我们会说任务空间的维度是3。
In this case, we would say that the dimension of a task space is 3.
它由三维矢量描述。
It’s described by a three-dimensional vector.
对于三维机器人，其末端执行器姿势由位置，坐标描述
For a three-dimensional robot whose end effector pose is described by the position, coordinates
X，Y和Z，其任务空间的维度也是3。
X, Y and Z, the dimension of its task space is also 3.
具有X，Y，Z位置以及俯仰角度，任务尺寸的机器人
The robot that has got X, Y, Z position and also a pitch angle, dimension of its task
空间是4。
space is 4.
并且，对于类似工业机器人的东西，其末端执行器姿势由位置描述
And, for something like an industrial robot whose end effector pose is described by position
X，Y，Z和方向可用三个角度描述，例如滚动，俯仰，
X, Y, Z and orientation which could be described by three angles, for instance, roll, pitch,
偏航角，其任务空间的维数为6。
yaw angles, the dimension of its task space is 6.
在我们生活的三维世界和机器人居住的世界里，事实并非如此
In the three-dimensional world in which we live and which the robots live, it’s not
可以给出任务空间维度6。
possible to have a task space dimension be given 6.
现在，真正重要的约束是，为了达到所有的任务空间，
Now, the really important constraint is that in order to reach all of the task space, the
配置空间的尺寸应大于或等于尺寸
dimension of the configuration space should be greater than or equal to the dimension
任务空间。
of the task space.
为了使这个具体，让我们再看看我们应该的2自由度臂
To make this concrete, let’s look again at the 2-degree freedom arm which we should
现在非常熟悉。
be quite familiar with by now.
末端效应器姿势是任务空间的一个元素，任务空间是一个子集
The end effector pose is an element of the task space and the task space is a subset
实数的二维空间。
of the two-dimensional space of real numbers.
末端效应器姿势可以用一对两个实数来描述。
End effector pose can be described by a pair of two real numbers.
该机器人的配置空间是包含Q1和Q2的矢量，两者
The configuration space for this robot is a vector that comprises Q1 and Q2, the two
关节角度。
joint angles.
配置空间也是实数二维空间的子集
The configuration space is also a subset of the two-dimensional space of real numbers
因为关节配置可以用一对实数来描述，即Q1和
because the joint configuration can be described by a pair of real numbers, that is Q1 and
Q2。
Q2.
对于3自由度臂，末端执行器姿势由三个数字X，Y和表示
For the 3-degree of freedom arm, the end effector pose is described by three numbers, X, Y and
西塔。
Theta.
所以，我们现在说任务空间是所有可能位置集合的子集
So, we say now that the task space is a subset of the set of all possible positions and the
我们用S表示的所有可能方向的子集。配置空间是
subset of all possible orientations which we denote by S. The configuration space is
包含Q1，Q2和Q3的矢量，并且是三维空间的子集
a vector comprising Q1, Q2 and Q3 and that is a subset of the three dimensional space
实数。
of real numbers.
到现在为止，我相信你已经掌握了这一点。
By now, I’m sure you’re getting the hang of this.
在这种情况下，任务空间是r立方体的一个子集，是三维真实的集合
In this case, the task space is a subset of r cubed, the set of three-dimensional real
数字。
numbers.
并且，配置空间也是实数的三维空间的子集。
And, the configuration space is also a subset of three-dimensional space of real numbers.
笛卡尔龙门机器人是一种特殊情况，因为关节坐标直接映射
A Cartesian Gantry robot is a special case because the joint coordinates directly map
到最后的效应器姿势。
on to the end effector pose.
关节坐标实际上是长度X，Y和Z.
The joint coordinates are in fact the lengths X, Y and Z.
4自由度SCARA机器人手臂具有由位置描述的末端执行器姿势
A 4-degree of freedom SCARA robot arm has an end effector pose described by a position
X，Y和Z以及偏航角。
X, Y and Z and a yaw angle.
所以，我们会说它的任务空间是r立方体的一个子集，所有可能的集合
So, we would say that its task space is a subset of r cubed, the set of all possible
位置，以及所有可能方向的集合。
positions, and the set of all possible orientations.
它的配置空间是四维数量，它包括三个旋转
Its configuration space is a four-dimensional quantity and it comprises the three rotational
关节角度和工具的垂直位移。
joint angles and a vertical displacement of the tool.
4自由度并联连杆机器人同样具有四维任务空间。
A 4-degree of freedom parallel link robot, again, has a four-dimensional task space.
它能够控制末端执行器的位置和方向，并且具有四维效果
It’s able to control the position and orientation of the end effector and it has a four-dimensional
配置空间。
configuration space.
底座上有四个电机通过连接到末端执行器的连接。
There are four motors located at the base connected by links to the end effector.
我们之前看过的四个联合教育机器人有一个四维任务空间
The four joint educational robot that we looked at before has a four-dimensional task space
这可以通过位置X，Y，Z和俯仰角及其配置来描述
which can be described by a position X, Y, Z and a pitch angle, and its configuration
也是四维的，因为这个机器人有四个旋转关节。
is also four-dimensional because there are four rotational joints in this robot.
同样的事情适用于NAO机器人的手臂。
The same thing applies for an arm of the NAO robot.
对于如此处所示的6自由度臂，任务空间是SE3的子集，即
For a 6-degree of freedom arm such as shown here, the task space is a subset of SE3, the
三维空间中所有可能位置的集合以及所有可能方向的集合
set of all possible positions in three-dimensional space and the set of all possible orientations
在三维空间。
in three-dimensional space.
所有这些机器人的配置空间也是六维的。
The configuration space of all these robots is also six-dimensional.
它们都有六个关节或6个自由度。
They all have six joints or 6 degrees of freedom.
工业机器人和航天飞机臂有六个旋转关节。
The industrial robot and the space shuttle arm have got six rotational joints.
然而，斯坦福大学的手臂有五个旋转关节和一个滑动关节。
Whereas, the Stanford arm has got five rotational joints and one sliding joint.
这是一个非常特殊的情况。
This is a very special case.
这是一个具有大量旋转关节的机器人。
This is a robot with a very large number of rotational joints.
该机器人的任务空间与上一张幻灯片上的机器人完全相同。
The task space of this robot is exactly the same as the robots on the previous slide.
末端执行器姿势由其位置和方向描述。
The end effector pose is described by its position and by its orientation.
它有六个维度。
It’s got six dimensions.
但是，像这样的机器人的配置空间可能非常庞大。
But, the configuration space for a robot like this could be quite massive.
我实际上并不知道这个机器人有多少关节，但我猜它是
I don’t actually know how many joints this robot’s got, but I’m guessing that it’s
有一百个关节。
got a hundred joints.
所以，我要说它的配置空间是100维空间的一个子集
So, I’m going to say that its configuration space is a subset of the 100-dimensional space
实数。
of real numbers.
因此，在这种情况下，配置空间的维度大于该维度
So, in this case, the dimension of the configuration space is greater than the dimension of the
任务空间。
task space.
我们称之为冗余机器人。
We call this a redundant robot.
冗余机器人的一个优点是刀尖可以实现任何位置和
An advantage of the redundant robot is that the tool-tip can achieve any position and
方向就像一个6自由度的工业机器人，但它的附加
orientation just like a 6-degree of freedom industrial robot does, but with its additional
自由度，它还可以控制手臂的形状。
degrees of freedom, it can also control the shape of the arm.
因此，它可以控制末端执行器的姿势和手臂的形状。
So, it can control the pose of the end effector and the shape of the arm.
只有六个关节的工业机器人只能控制末端执行器的姿势。
An industrial robot with only six joints can only control the pose of the end effector.
它不能选择其手臂的任意配置形状。
It can’t choose an arbitrary configurational shape of its arm.
我们描述机器人手臂的另一种方式是配置字符串和这个
Another way that we describe robot arms is in terms of a configuration string and this
是一串字符，每个关节一个字符，字符是Rfor
is a string of characters, one character per joint and the character is either an R for
用于棱柱或滑动接头的旋转接头或P.
a rotational joint or P for a prismatic or sliding joint.
所以，在这里我们可以看到三种截然不同的机器人的配置字符串。
So, here we can see the configuration strings for three quite different sorts of robot.